<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and a playne introduction, teachyng how to pronounce the letters of the British tong, (now co[m]menly called Walsh) wherby an English man shal not only w[ith] ease read the said tong rightly: but markyng ye same wel, it shal be a meane for him with one labour and diligence to attaine to the true and natural pronuncation of other expediente and most excellente langauges Set forth by W. Salesburye.</title>
            <author>Salesbury, William, 1520?-1600?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101926</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837729</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11356)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and a playne introduction, teachyng how to pronounce the letters of the British tong, (now co[m]menly called Walsh) wherby an English man shal not only w[ith] ease read the said tong rightly: but markyng ye same wel, it shal be a meane for him with one labour and diligence to attaine to the true and natural pronuncation of other expediente and most excellente langauges Set forth by W. Salesburye.</title>
                  <author>Salesbury, William, 1520?-1600?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [R. Grafton for] Roberte Crowley, dwellyng in Elye rentes in Holburne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The yere of our Lord. M.D.L. [1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Welsh language --  Pronunciation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2069:1"/>
            <p>A briefe and a playne introduction, teachyng how to pronounce the letters in the Britiſh tong, (now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly called Walſh) wherby an Engliſh man ſhal not only w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eaſe read the ſaid tong rightly: but markyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame wel, it ſhal be a meane for him with one labour and diligence to attaine to the true and natural pronunciation of other expediente and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente languages Set forth by W. Saleſburye.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Roberte Crowley, dwellyng in Elye rentes in Holburne. The yere of our Lord. M.D.L.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>¶Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2069:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To hys louynge frende, maiſter Rychard Colyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne. Wyllyam Saleſburye wyſheth proſperous healthe, and perfecte felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE naturall inclination, the gentle amitie, and the feruent loue and fauoure, whych you mooſte affectuouſlye, entierlye, and perfitlye, do not onely owe, but haue, beare, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute towarde me, my contrye, and contrye language: and againe the ſodayne ſemblable vehemente affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whych I moſte comparable and ardent, mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and dulye do beare towards you: hath cauſed me to abortiat, (if I myght ſpeake my contry la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gage, I neaded not to borowe the latine terme, neyther make anye further explanation thereof) and to bring forthe my late conceyued chyld before hys naturall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated tyme of byrthe.</p>
            <p>But what than? For thys euyll chaunce there lyeth none other remedye, but eyther (if he ſeme to haue his lineamentes tyghtly proportionated, thoughe as yet ſomewhat lumpyſhe) to lycke hym hereafter (as the Beare doeth hyr whelpe) into a more perfecte ſhape: eyther els, if he ſhal appeare ouermuche monſtruous to take hym and throw him into the botomeles floud of Lethe, where then he ſhall neyther greue the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes hertes, nor yet offende the eyen of kynne, nor ſtraunger.</p>
            <p>But peraduenture ye wyll ſaye, what by all thys? ye ſpeake in parables, but I pray you frende Saleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burye ſpeake plaine Englyſhe to me. Well therfore to appeare in mine owne likenes, and to be as plaine as
<pb facs="tcp:2069:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the playne of Saleſburie. The ſayde child is thys boke, whom you ſo inordinately deſire to go abrode before the appoynted ſeaſon by the determination of the graue, diſcrete and pithy Poete Horace Flactus, whoſe verſes be not farre from theſe in ſentence.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Whan that thy reſtles penne, of fame hath ought contrivd:</l>
               <l>At Metius eare ſe that thou tune, the cord in work reuivd</l>
               <l>And let them iudge therin, whoſe heares be griſely growne;</l>
               <l>Let midle age, let vnripe yeres, theron their iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſowne</l>
               <l>Than maiſt thou well at wil (nine yeres in trial ſpente)</l>
               <l>Set forth the work of wiſdomes braine, that the in lot is lent</l>
               <l>The ſounde eſcaped once, can not be called backe:</l>
               <l>But ſhut vp thoughts in hert mai be, ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded wher they lack.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yet neuertheles, for your faithful frendſhyps ſake I wyll not onely wynke at thys, but euen aduiſedly wyl forſake the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t counſaile of the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus admoniſhynge. A fole differeth nothinge from a wiſe man whiles he kepeth ſilence: yea, and I am not aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to publiſhe theſe vnſauoury trifles (for the ſmall commoditie that you ſhall perceiue by them) amonge the honourable theatre, and worſhipfull company of the learned, whiche moſte plentuouſly (thankes be to the Lorde) habound now in euery place.</p>
            <p>But of whence than commeth this vnſhamefaſte boldnes? Marye of a licence graunted and prouided forme by the verye ſame Poete, whoſe owne praiſe, metre, and wordes (ne leſt by vnapt traduction of the ſame, I ſhould diſgrace the diuine poeticall maieſtie) I wyll here ſubſcribe.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>— hoc tibi dictum</l>
               <l>Tolle memor, certis medium et tolerabile rebus</l>
               <l>Recte concedi: conſultus iuris et actor</l>
               <l>Lauſarum mediocris, abeſt virtute diſerti</l>
               <l>Meſſale, nec ſcit quantum Caſelitus Aulus</l>
               <l>Sed tamen in pretio eſt.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:2069:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Beſides thys, the head learned man of all our tyme euen Eraſmus Roterodamus, holdeth ſoore on my parte, for it is a true ſaid ſawe (ſayth he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is not written ſo yll a boke, but it is worthy the reading for ſome conſideration. And againe, he affirmeth euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the ſame place that it is expediente to heare the vnlearned playe the oratours or preachers, whereby it maye appeare, what ſhall be decent, and what not.</p>
            <p>Therfore (I ſaye) be it expedient or rather tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to admitte as well ſome ſuch vnlearned writters as haue not the grace to obſerue <hi rend="small">To prepon</hi> or comly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes euery where, and at all tymes. Amongeſt whiche ſorte I wyl not diſdayne to be accounted, ſeyng I am adſured to ſatiſfie in ſome parte your minde, thoughe it be but ſlenderly to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And in as much as I am fulli perſwaded that you be the man to whom boeth for good learnyng &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte iudgement therein, and for the fauour pretended towarde this feble enterpriſe, I neades muſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thys boke (if for the littlenes it may be iuſtely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a boke) not onelye to be redde, corrected, &amp; perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but alſo to be defended frome the cancred maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous checkes of all thoſe, who at all times canne be at better layſure to rebuke other mens doinges, than to do ought them ſelues. Thus fare ye hartelye well.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Thauies Inne in Holburne more haſtely, than ſpedelye. <date>M.D.L.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2069:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶Wyllyam Saleſburye to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not longe after (gentle Reader) that I had compyled a little Dictionarye for the vſe and behoue of my contry men, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Walſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the ſame ſette forthe and publiſhed at the kinges hyghnes licence and pleaſure, but there came certayne perſons vnto me,<note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makynge of thys boke.</note> whereof ſome were Englyſh marchers bordering vpon Wales: and ſome not ſkilled in the Walſhe tonge, neuertheles hauyng good and honeſte occaſions, eyther for their promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and lyuynges, eyther els for trade of Marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and other their affayres to be conuerſante in the ſayde contrye of Wales, and peraduenture ſometime chaunce to be amonge them that can not a worde of Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>And ſome other were ſuch Walſhmen that had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought vp from their youth and tender age, oute of the precincte of their natiue contrye, who thoughte it reproch to be vtterly ignoraunt in their mother tong, hauing a mind alſo to come to ſome knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, wherby they myght y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rather (ſemyng leſſe ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g) renewe frendſhyp and familiaritie with their contrye folke and frendes, (whyche thynge otherwyſe they coulde not ſo conuenientlye brynge to paſſe) &amp; mooſte chiefely to edifie them, as well in ciuyle inſtitutions, as in godlye doctryne.</p>
            <p>Nowe the other ſome, were ſuch Engliſhe men as had not ſo vrgente a cauſe, nor ſo earneſt an occaſion to trauell in thys behalfe, but yet were they ſo feruent (as it ſemed bi their importune requeſt) as they (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſpake of before) whom the Grekes with one propre
<pb facs="tcp:2069:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> terme cal Philoglottous,<note place="margin">Langage louers</note> whoſe ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle herted diſpoſition is alwaies addicte, bente, &amp; geuen to be ſene in al lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, but ſpeciallye of their owne felow ſubiectes and contrey menne, thoughe they purchaſe there by but ſmall gaynes, lucre, or wynnyng, whiche thynges be the honied ſwete baytes of the auaricious beaſtly miſers, and contrarywyſe the defiaunce of all liberal and noble ſtomakes.</p>
            <p>Whan (I ſaye) ſuche menne reſorted vnto me to queſtion whether the ſayde Dictionarye was as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differente for Englyſhe men to learne Walſhe by, as for Walſhe men to learne Engliſhe: I anſwered that it was not al ſo indifferent. The reſon why, if I ſhold declare it, ſhoulde not be eaſely perceyued but of the learned, who do vnderſtande it already.</p>
            <p>Than emongeſt other communication hadde, they aſked, whether the pronounciation of the Letters in Walſhe, dyd dyffer from the Englyſhe ſoundynge of them? And I ſayde verye muche. And ſo they percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge that they coulde not profite in buildynge anye further on the Walſhe, lackynge the foundation and grounde worcke (whyche was the Walſhe pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of the letters) deſiered me efte ſones to write vnto them (as they hadde ſene me do in Walſh to my contryemen, to introducte them to pronounce the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Englyſhe like) a fewe engliſhe rules of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall power of the letters in our tonge.</p>
            <p>And ſo than, in as muche as I was not onelye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the premiſes, but alſo further perſwaded that neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r any inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience or miſchefe might enſue or grow therof, but rather the encreaſe of mutuall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and brotherly loue, and continuall frendſhyppe,
<pb facs="tcp:2069:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſome commoditie at the leaſte wiſe, to ſuche as be deſierous to be occupied thereaboutes. As for all other, euen as it ſhall neuer worke them pleaſure, ſo ſhall it no diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Euen therefore at the laſt, I haue bene ſo bold as to enterpryſe (condeſcendynge to ſuche mens honeſte requeſte) to inuent and wryte theſe plaine, ſimple, and rude rudimentes of the Walſhe pronunciation of the letters, moſte humbly deſierynge the Readers to accepte them wyth no leſſe beniuolente hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie than I hertely pretended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, whan I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to treate of the matter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2069:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶The Pronunciation of the the lettters in the Brytyſhe tonge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE letters in the Britiſhe or Walſhe tonge, haue the ſame fygure &amp; faſhion as they haue in Englyſh, and be in numbre as here vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the Alphabet appeareth.</p>
            <p>A b c ch d dd e f ff g h i k l ll m n o p r ſ t th v u w y.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the vowels. a e i o u w y.</p>
            <p>Theſe two vowels a, w, be mutable.</p>
            <p>The dipthonges be theſe, and be pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced after the very Greke pronunciation.<note place="margin">As euag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geliou.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>Ae ai au aw ay</item>
                  <item>ei ew</item>
                  <item>ia ie io iw</item>
                  <item>oe ow oy</item>
                  <item>uw</item>
                  <item>wy.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe letters be called conſonauntes. b c ch d dd f ff g k l ll m n o p r ſ t th v.</p>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The pronunciation of A.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> In Britiſhe or Walſhe in euery worde hath the true pronunciation of A in latine. And it is neuer ſounded like the diphthonge au, as the Frenche men ſound it commynge before
<pb facs="tcp:2069:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> m. or .n. in their tonge, nor ſo fully in the mouth as the Germaines ſounde it in this worde Magen: Neyther yet as it is pronounced in Engliſhe, whan it commeth before ge, ll. ſh. tch: For in theſe wordes and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in englyſhe, Domage, heritage, language, aſhe, laſhe, watch, calme, call (a) is thought to decline to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the ſounde of theſe dipthonges ai, au, and the wordes to be reade in thys wiſe, domaige, heritaige, languaige, aiſhe, waitche, caul, caulme. But as I ſaid before, a. in walſh hath alwaies but one ſound what ſo euer letter it folowe or go before, as in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ap, cap. whyche haue the ſame pronunciation &amp; ſignification in both the tonges.</p>
               <p>Muche leſſe hathe a, ſuche varietie in Walſhe, as hath Aleph in Hebrue (which alone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> points altered) hath the ſounde of euery vowell. Howbeit that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, deriuation, and the plurell numbre, do ofte times in the commune walſhe ſpeache chaunge a, for e. as in theſe wordes, vnweith, ſeithfed, ebeſtyl. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles e. then ſucceadeth, and is alſo written in the ſtede of a. ſo that the Reader ſhall neuer be troubled therewyth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of B.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>, In Walſhe is vniuerſallye reade and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced as it is in Englyſhe. Albeit whan a word begynneth wyth b, and is ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moe wordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng in a reaſon, the phraſe and the maner of the Walſhe ſpeache (muche lyke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Hebrues idiome) ſhall alter the ſounde of that b.<note place="margin">So do theſe wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, cuui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul, vicſes whych be deriued of cubitꝰ, cubiculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, biſextus,</note> into the ſounde of the Hebrue letter that they call
<pb facs="tcp:2069:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Beth not daggeſſed, or of the Greke Veta, eyther els of v. beynge conſonant in latine or Englyſh, as thus. Where as b. in thys walſhe worde bys a fynger, is the primitiue (or if I ſhold borow the Hebrue terme) the radicall letter, whyche commynge in the contexte of a reaſon ſhall not than be called b. but v. as in this texte: I vys: his finger. And ſometime b. ſhal be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into m, as for an enſample. vy mys: my fynger. And yet for all the alteration of this letter b, and of diuerſe other (as ye ſhall perceiue hereafter) whyche by their nature be chaungeable one for an other, it ſhal nothynge let nor hynder anye man, from the true and propre readinge of the letters ſo altered.</p>
               <p>For as ſone as the ydiome or proprietie of the tong receyueth one letter for an other, the radicall is omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and left away: and the acceſſorie or the letter that commeth in ſtede of the radicall, is forthwyth wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſo pronounced after his owne nature &amp; power as it is playne inoughe, by the former exemple.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes that ſuch tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſmutation of letters in ſpeakinge (for therin conſiſteth all the difficultie) is mooſte diligentlye to be marked, obſerued,<note place="margin">☜</note> and taken hede vnto, of him that ſhall delite to ſpeake walſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>Howe C is pronounced.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>, Maketh K. for loke what power hath c.<note place="margin">As witne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſeth cicut deducted of cicut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, natali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of natalitis. accen of accentus diſcipul of diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus, ciſt of ciſta.</note> in Engliſhe or in Latine, whan it commeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a. o. u. that ſame ſhall it haue in walſhe before anye vowel, dypthonge, or conſonant what ſo euer it be.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Howe be it ſome of our time do vſe to wryte .k. ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than, c. where wryters in tymes paſte haue lefte c. wrytten in their auncient bokes, ſpecially before .a. o. u. and before all maner conſonantes, and in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ende of wordes. Alſo otherſome ther be, that ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nowe .c. as .g. in the laſte termination of a worde: An exemple: oc, koc, lloc: whiche be moſte commune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly redde, og, kog, llog.</p>
               <p>Furthermore it is the nature of c. to be turned into ch,<note place="margin">Conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning togi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of words o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe called a reaſon. Carw is the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute word</note> and other whyles into, g. But I meane this, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a worde that begynneh wyth .c. cometh in conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as thus: Carw, a harte, Ewic a charw, a hind and a harte. Either els whan .c. or .k. (for they be boeth one in effecte) is the fyrſte letter of a worde that ſhall be compounded, as for an example: Angraff, angred, angriſt, whyche be compounded of an, and of kraff, kred, kriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of ch.</head>
               <p>Ch, doeth whollye agree wyth the pronunciation of ch, alſo in the Germayne tonge, of the Greke Chy, or the Hebrue Cheth. or of gh, in Englyſhe:</p>
               <p>And it hath no affinitie at al wyth ch, in Englyſhe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte in theſe wordes, Mychael, Mychaelmas, and a fewe ſuche other. Ch alſo whan it is the radical let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in anye Walſhe worde, remayneth immutable in euery place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of D.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>, Is redde in Walſhe none otherwyſe than in Engliſhe, ſauynge onely that oftentimes d, in the firſte ſillables ſhall be turned into dd, reſemblynge muche Daleth the Hebrue d. And ſometyme whan a worde begynning wyth d, is compounded wyth (an) the d, ſhall ſlyp awaye, as anawn, of an, and dawne: anoeth, of an and doeth.</p>
               <p>Dd is nothyng lyke of pronunciation to dd. in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſh or latin: For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> double dd. in Walſh hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of dhelta, or dhaleth, daſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> raphe, or of d. betwixt .ii. vowels in the Hiſpaniſh tong, either els of th. as they be communelye ſounded in theſe englyſhe wordes, the, that, thys, thyne: Neyther do I meane nothynge leſſe than that dd. in Walſhe be ſounded at anye tyme after the ſounde of th. in theſe wordes of Englyſhe, wyth thynne, thanke. But ye ſhall fynde in olde wrytten Englyſhe bokes, a letter hauyng the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of a Romayne y. that youre aunceſters called dhorn, whych was of one efficacie wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walſh dd. And there be nowe in ſome contryes in England that pronounce dd. euen in theſe wordes<note n="*" place="margin">An in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> addes, fedder, accordinge as they be pronounced in the walſhe.</p>
               <p>And ye muſte note that dd. in walſh is not called dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dd. neyther is it a double letter (though it ſemeth ſo to be) wherfore it doeth not fortifie nor harden the ſillable that it is in, but cauſeth it to be a great deale more thycke, ſofte, &amp; ſmothe. For he that firſte added to the ſeconde d. mente thereby to aſpirate the d. and ſignifie that it ſhold be more lightly ſounded, and not the contrary.</p>
               <p>But I thynke it had be eaſier, more mete, and leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:2069:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtraunge to the Reader, if that he hadde put h. after the former d, in a ſigne of aſperation, than to adde an other d, therto.</p>
               <p>And as it ſemeth it is not paſſynge thre or foure, C. yeres ago, ſynce they began to double their d, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that tyme by lykelihode they vſed one conſtante maner of pronunciation of their letters, euen as the Hebrues did at the begynnynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>Howe E ought to be ſounded</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>, Without anye exception hath one perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt pronunciation in Walſh, and that is the ſelfe pronunciation of Epſylon in Greke, or of e, in the latine beynge ſounded aryghte, or e. in Engliſh, as it is ſounded in theſe wordes, a were wreke, breke, wreſte.</p>
               <p>And the learner muſte take good hede, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer do reade the ſayd e, as it is read in theſe Englyſh wordes, we, beleue: For than by ſo doynge, ſhall he either alter the ſignification of the worde wherin the ſame e, is ſo corruptelye reade, eyther els cauſe it to betoken nothynge at all in that ſpeache. Example: pe, ſignifieth in Englyſh and, if: now, if ye read it pi. than wyll it betoken thys letter p. or the byrde that ye call in englyſhe a Pye. And ſo gwe is, a webbe: but if ye ſounde e. as i. readinge it gwi: than hath it no ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the Walſhe.</p>
               <p>And leaſte peraduenture the forſayde example of the walſhe or ſtraunge tonge be ſomewhat obſcure, than take thys in your owne mother tonge for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of that other: wherbi ye ſhal perceyue that
<pb facs="tcp:2069:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the diuerſitie of pronunciation of e, in theſe Englyſhe wordes ſubſcribed hereafter, wyll alſo make them to haue diuerſe ſignifications, and they be theſe wordes, bere, pere, hele mele. Neyther yet do we vſe in Walſhe at anye tyme to wryte e, in the middle or laſt ſillables and to leaue it vnſpoken in readynge: as it is done by Scheua in hebrue, or as the maner of wrytyng and readynge of the ſame, is accuſtomed in englyſhe, as it ſhall be more manifeſte by theſe wordes that folowe: golde, ſylke, purenes, Chepeſyde: wherein (as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) e. is not written to the entent it myght be reade or ſpoken, but to mollifye the ſillable that it is put in.</p>
               <p>But nowe I am occaſioned to declyne and ſtraye ſomewhat frome my purpoſe,<note place="margin">An obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation for wrytinge of engliſh whiche in printynge can not ſo well be kepte.</note> and to reueale my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie to yonge wryters of Englyſhe, whoe (me thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) take ouer muche paynes, and beſtowe vnrequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite coſte (hauynge no reſpecte to the nature of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe endinge e.) in doublynge letters to harden the ſillable, and immediatlye they adde an, e (whyche is a ſigne of mittigatynge and ſoftenynge of the ſillable) after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letters ſo doubled, as thus: manne, worſhippe Godde, wotte, wyſhe, goodneſſe, hemme nette: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wordes wyth ſuche other like, myght wyth leſſe laboure, and as well for the purpoſe, be written on thys wyſe: ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n, worſhypp, Godd, wott, wyſh, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hemm, nett: or rather this: man, worſhyp, God, wot, wyſh, goodnes, hem net.</p>
               <p>For accordynge to the commen prouerbe, it is but foly to beſtowe more, where leſſe wyll ſerue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Howe F is communely ſounded.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg> In Walſhe and V beyng conſonant in walſh englyſhe, or latine, be ſo nyghe of ſounde that they vſe moſte communely to write in walſhe indifferentlye the one for the other. And I my ſelfe haue hearde Englyſhe men in ſome contryes of Englaude ſounde f. euen as we ſounde it in Walſhe for I haue marked their maner of pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation and ſpeciallye in ſoundyng theſe wordes: voure, viue, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigure, viſhe: where they woulde ſaye, foure, fiue, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſfigure, fyſhe. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But who ſo euer knoweth the ſounde of the letter called Digamma (whoſe figure is muche lyke F. but ouerwhelmed vpſydedowne, as ye ſee here <seg rend="invert">F</seg>) he ſhal alſo knowe thereby the verye ſounde of the ſyngle f.<note place="margin">Eolicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <seg rend="invert">F</seg>
                  </note> in Walſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of ff.</head>
               <p>ff In Walſhe hath but the ſame ſound that the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle f. hath in englyſhe. And they are fayne to vſe the double ff. for the ſingle f. bicauſe they haue abuſed f. in ſtede of v. a conſonante. But in ſuche wordes as haue p. for the firſt letter of their original (for to kepe the ortographie) they write ph. and not ff. as thus. Petr a Phawl, Peter and Paule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The pronunciation of G.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg> In euery worde in Walſhe ſoundeth as the Hebrue Gymel: or g. in Doutche, or as g. in Engliſhe ſoundeth before a o u. And marcke well that g. neuer ſoundeth in Walſhe as it
<pb facs="tcp:2069:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> doeth in engliſhe in theſe wordes, George, gynger.<note place="margin">G, is but verye ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into ch. Gwedy Gwad. Glas</note>
               </p>
               <p>G, alſo in walſhe ſometyme (whan it cometh in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) ſhall be turned into ch, and ſometyme elided or lefte cleane out of the word as thus: a chwedy hynny. iawn ne wad: koch ne las: and not koch ne glas.</p>
               <p>And otherwhile wordes compounded ſhall put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye g, as theſe do, ſerloyw, dulas: whoſe ſymple be theſe: ſer, gloyw: du glas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>Of the aſpiration H.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>, In euerye worde that it is wrytten in, in Walſhe, hathe hys aſpiration in ſpeakinge alſo, and is reade, euen as in theſe wordes of Engliſhe, hard, heard, hart, hurt: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where ſo euer h, is wrytten in walſhe, lette it be reade wyth all, and not holden ſtyll, as it is done in Frenche and Englyſhe in ſuche wordes as be deriued oute of latine as theſe, honeſt, habitation, humble ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite. &amp;c. Except whan h, is ſettled betwene two vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els in walſhe wordes: for than it forceth not greatlye whether h, be ſounded or not, as in theſe words that folowe: brenhin, kyhyr, mehein, gweheu, heheu, gwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hydd, gohir. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>, In Walſhe hath the mere pronunciation of i, in latine, as learned men in our tyme vſe to ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it, &amp; not as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their corrupt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation make a dipthong of it, ſaying: vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei, teibei, for vidi, tibi. But loke howe i, ſoundeth in
<pb facs="tcp:2069:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Englyſhe in theſe wordes: ſinging, ringing, drinking, winkinge, nighe, ſighe, might, right.</p>
               <p>So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, in euery ſyllabe in walſh hath eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſounde as e, hath in Englyſh in theſe woordes: we, ſe three, bee. And i, is neuer ſounded ſo broade in walſhe as it is in this Engliſh word<note n="*" place="margin">Ego</note> I. And beſide that i, is neuer conſonant in walſh, but euer remaining a vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, as it doeth in the Germayne tong, or as iota in the Greke. And bicauſe they that haue not taſted of the preceptes of Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer do not lightly vnderſtand what thys terme conſonant meaneth: I wyll ſpeake herein as playne as I can, for to induce them to vnderſtand my meanynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Whan i, is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note>Therfore whan we ſaye in ſpellynge m, a, ma: i, e, ie, ſt, e, ſte, maieſte: (or) I, e, Ie, ſ, u, s, ſus, Ieſus: nowe in theſe two wordes, maieſte and Ieſus: i, is conſonant.<note place="margin">Whan i, is a vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell.</note> But whan I ſpel on thys wyſe: i, per ſe, i, o-rk, ork, and wyth doynge them togyther, read iork: than i, is not called conſonant, but hath the name of a vowell.</p>
               <p>And therefore if ye liſte to reade ryghtlye Walſhe wordes in whom i, is wrytten, an other vowell im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately folowyng (for therin els is there no hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce for the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge reader) than muſt you harken (howe i,<note place="margin">I for Y. I in thys word iye, (oculus) is now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munelye written &amp; read as it is in wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe.</note> which, I wryte for y) is ſounded in theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe wordes: i-ane, i-arde, i-arne, ielde, i<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>elk, i-elle, ielow, iere, iok, iong, iougth, Iorke, iou: And though theſe wordes be written here now wyth i, in the firſt letter of euery one, yet it is ment that you ſhould read them as the i, were y, and as they had be wrytten on on thys faſhyon: yane, yarde, yelde, yelke, yell, yelow,
<pb facs="tcp:2069:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> yere, yok, yong, yougth yorke, you.</p>
               <p>Nowe I truſte that the dulleſt wytted chyld that neuer reade but two lynes, perceaueth ſo familiar a rudimente.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of K.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>, Foloweth the rule of c, in euerye poynte, and therefore loke for the effecte of k, where it is treated of the letter c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of L.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>, Hath none other differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in ſound in walſh than in Englyſh. And note that it nether cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a, nor o, whan they come before it, to ſounde anye more fullier in the mouthe, than they do els ſounde, commyng before any other letter. And for the playner vnderſtandynge thereof, loke in the rules that entreate of the ſounde of a, and o.</p>
               <p>And marcke whan ſoeuer ye ſe l, to be the fyrſte letter of a worde, that eyther the ſame worde cometh in conſtruction, eyther els the worde is of an other language, and but vſurped in walſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>Of the ſtraunge ſounde of double .ll.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Ll, can not be declared anye thynge lyke to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in wrytynge, but onely by mouth: if ye than wil learne howe it ought to be ſounded: For (as it is ſaid before of d) ſo the ſecond l, is added in ſtede of h: but loke howe Lambda comming before Iota is ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Greke: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo pronounce well, in the walſh. And if ye coulde hit kindely on the right and iuſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of lh, thus aſpirated: not leauyng vnſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the entier efficacitie and the whole ſtrength of the aſpiration: than ſhoulde not you be farre diſſonant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true ſounde of our walſhe ll.</p>
               <p>For the Walſh l, is ſpoken the tonge bowed vp a lyttle to the roufe of the mouth, and wyth that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what extendinge it ſelfe betwexte the fore teathe, the lyppes not all touchynge togyther (but leauyng ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it were for a wyndowe) the ryghte wyke of the mouthe for to breathe oute wyth a thycke aſpirated ſpirite the ſame ll. But as I ſayde before, and if ye wyl haue the verye walſhe ſounde of thys letter: geue eare to a walſhman whan he ſpeaketh culltell, which betokeneth a knyfe in Engliſhe: or ellyll a goſte:</p>
               <p>The Walſh man or the Hiſpanyard compoſe their mouthes muche after one faſhion wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their ll, ſauynge that the walſheman vttereth it wyth a more thicker and a more mightier ſpirite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of M.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>, In Walſh hath ſuch a ſounde as ye heare it haue in Engliſh or latine: but yet it is one of the letters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be chaungeable in conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thus: mwy, moo: llai ne vwy, leſſe or
<pb facs="tcp:2069:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> more, mwyvwy, more (and) more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of N.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>, Is none otherwiſe ſounded in Walſh than in Engliſhe: but ſometyme (after the latyne maner) whan it commeth before b, or p, in compoſition, it is tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turned into m, as ym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaen, whiche is compounded of yn and blaen: am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parch, of an and parch, amp wyll, of an and pwyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of O.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>, In Walſhe is ſounded accordynge to the ryght ſoundynge of it in latine: eyther els as the ſounde of o, is in theſe Engliſhe wordes: a doo, a roo, a too: and o, neuer ſoundeth in Walſhe as it doeth in theſe wordes of Engliſhe: to do, two. But marke that o, in Walſhe goynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore l, ll, ſoundeth nothynge more boyſtouſe, that is to ſaye, that it inclineth to the ſounde of the dipthonge ou (as it doeth in Englyſhe) no more than if it hadde gone be fore anye other letter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of P.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>, In Walſhe differeth not from the Englyſh ſounde of p: but p commyng in conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on foloweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rules of the Hebrue phe: ſaue ſomtime it is turned into b, as thus: pedwar bump, for pump. And ſometyme p, in compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is chaunged alſo into b, as wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay ymbell for
<pb facs="tcp:2069:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> ympell. And one whyle it is left out of the compound wordes: as whan theſe wordes: kymell, kymorth, be written for kympell, kymporth.</p>
               <p>And an other whyle our tonge geueth vs to ſound it, as it were an h, as whan we ſaye: ymhle, ymhlwy, ymhlas, for ymple, ymplwy, ymplas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of Q.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>, Is not receiued among the numbre of the letters in walſhe as yet, but k ſupplyeth his rowme, &amp; vſurpeth his office in euery place. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Greks are fayne to practice the ſame feacte, as ye may ſe it done. Luc. ii. where Kyriniou, is wryten for Quirino.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of R.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>, Is ſounded alike in Walſhe and Englyſhe, but r, in walſhe for the mooſte parte is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced wyth aſpiration, eſpeciallye beynge the fyrſte letter of the worde. And for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration h, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely put to an other r, as they playe by d, and l, euen thus: rrwygwyd, rrodres, rringill, Rufain: But the maner of ſome is to write one greate captall R, (whan it is the firſte letter of a word) for the leſſer double rr. Alſo r, ſerueth the turn that n, doeth in Engliſhe, that is to wytte, to be putte betwene vowels metynge togyther in two ſondrye wordes, for to ſtoppe the vncomely gapyng in ſpeach as ye ſhall perceyue by theſe wordes: y-r awr: a-n houre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The ſounde of .S.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>, Soundeth in Walſhe as it doeth in latine: neyther hathe it two diuers ſoundes as it hath in Englyſhe or French, for when it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth betwene two vowels in theſe two lan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guages, it is ſo remiſſely and lithly ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded as it were a z, as by theſe two wordes of boeth the tonges it is manifeſtly proued. Faiſant a Feſant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of T.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>, Lykewyſe hath but one ſounde, and that is as the latines ſounde it in theſe wordes: atat tute, tegit: Neyther do I meane that t, in Walſhe is ſounded at anye tyme like th, as ſome barbarous liſpers do, who depraue the true la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine pronunciation, readynge Amath, for amat, dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith for dederit. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Howbeit marke well thys exception, that t, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reade like c, thorowout the walſhe tonge, as it is communely read of Engliſhe men in latine verbales endinge in tio, as <hi rend="small">pronunciatio, electio, ſubiectio. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marke alſo, that it is the nature of t, to be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to d, and ſometyme into th, and ſome other tyme it is ſo lyghtly ſpoken, that the t, is quite lefte awaye, and there remayneth but the h, in ſtede of the t. But thys is to be vnderſtand whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> t, is the firſt letter of a word ſet in conſtrction to be conſtrued or builte togither on thys faſhion: Na thric ynhy dwy ne dair.</p>
               <p>For before they be hewed, ſquared, and ioyned togyther wyth theyr tenantes and morteſſes, they lye
<pb facs="tcp:2069:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> in rude and vndreſſed timbre after this maner of ſort: Na tryc ynty dwy ne tair.<note place="margin">The abſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lute wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Furthermore t, in deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is left out of the deriued words, that they might ſounde more pleaſaunte to the eare, as ye maye take theſe for an example: chwano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of chwant: gwnoc of gwynt: monweni of monwent: henieu of haint. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of Th.</head>
               <p>Th, hath the ſemblable and lyke ſounde in Walſh as it hath in Englyſhe in theſe wordes: thorowe, thycke, and thynne: but it is neuer ſo lythlye ſpoken, as it is communly ſounded in theſe other wordes: that, thou thine, this.</p>
               <p>Moreouer th, wrytten for the fyrſte letter of anye worde, ſheweth the ſame word to be than in conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For there is no walſhe worde ſtandinge abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelye that hath th, for his fyrſte letter but t, is hys natiue and originall letter, for the whyche in conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction th, is communely vſed. Neither yet do we vſe to write th, in anye worde, and to reade the ſame as t, or d, as it is communely done in theſe englyſh wordes: Thomas, throne, threaſure, Thauie sinne: whych be moſte vniuerſallye ſpoken after thys ſorte:<note place="margin">Thauies inne.</note> Tomas, trone, treaſure, Dauies inne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of V beyng conſonant.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">There be but fewe words in Walſhe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beginne wyth v.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>,</hi> Speciallye beynge wrytten in thys maner of faſhion v, ſoundeth in walſh as in engliſh or latine, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a conſonant. And it light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neuer begynneth a word, except the word
<pb facs="tcp:2069:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> be conſtructed &amp; ioyned with one or more wordes. For than b, or m, beynge the originall or radical let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is tranſmuted or chaunged (accordynge to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruitie of the tonge) into v, a conſonant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of u, beynge a vowell.</head>
               <p>But u, wrytten after this maner u, is a vowell, and ſoundeth as the vulgare Engliſhe people ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it in theſe wordes of Englyſhe: truſte, bury, buſye.</p>
               <p>But knowe well that it is neuer ſounded in walſh, as it is done in any of theſe two Englyſhe wordes (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtanding the diuerſe ſound of them) ſure, lucke. Alſo the ſound of u, in French, or ü, wyth two pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ouer the heade in Teutche, or the Scottiſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation of u, alludeth ſomewhat nere vnto the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of it in Walſhe, thoughe yet none of them all, doeth ſo exactly (as I thynke) expreſſe it, as the Hebraick Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buts doeth.</p>
               <p>For the Walſh u, is none other thing, but a meane ſounde betwyxte u, and y, beynge latyne vowels.</p>
               <p>And therefore who ſo euer wyll deſtinctlye learne the Walſh ſound of u, let hym once geue eare to a walſh man, whan he ſpeaketh in walſhe, the wordes that ſignifie in engliſhe obedience (or) one<note n="*" place="margin">Acus, ſeu palea</note> chaffe: whych be theſe in Walſhe .uvudd, uſſun. And this vowell u, alone amonge all the letters in Walſhe, ſwarueth in ſounde from the true latine pronunciation. Neither is u thus ſounded, but of the vnlearned,<note place="margin">u abuſed for Y.</note> who abuſe it for y, &amp; that more often of vs that be of Northwales, than of the Southren Walſhman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The ſounde of w.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>, In Walſhe and engliſhe hathe but one fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and power, though it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth to haue two diuerſe names, for in Englyſhe ye call it double uu, &amp; in Walſhe we geue it the name of a ſyngle u, but than ſoundynge it after the Latine pronunciation.</p>
               <p>But the leſſer Greke o, ioyned togyther wyth the Greke y, made a dipthonge, or the Hebraik Vaf. <hi rend="small">cum puncto ſchurek in ventre,</hi> eyther oo, in theſe englyſhe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cables: booke, looke, boorde, woorde, ſhall rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe hys name, than hys propre efficacie.</p>
               <p>But hys owne power, and peculier office in Walſhe, ſhall there no letter nor letters more preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſet it forth than the w, it ſelfe, wyth the Englyſhe pronunciation. For althoughe the Germaynes vſe a w, yet in ſome wordes ſound they it (to my hearing) as the forther u, were a vowell, and the latter a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant, where we the Britons ſounde both uu, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly togyther as one vowell, wythout anye ſondrye di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, but beynge alwayes eyther the forther or the later parte of a dipthonge in englyſh on this wiſe: wyth, awe: and in Walſhe as thus: wyth, awen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of X.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">X</seg>, Is not founde as yet in the Walſh Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet: for the walſh ſpeach hath no nede of his office: bicauſe that ſuche walſhe wordes as be deducted of the Latine, turne their x, into ſ, as do theſe: crws, nos, esteſtenna, escommuna, eſtran, bic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whiche come of <hi rend="small">Crux, nox, extendo, excommunico, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traneus
<pb facs="tcp:2069:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> biſextus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>The ſounde of Y.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>, Is ſounded in Walſh as it is theſe Engliſh words: yn, ſynne, ys, thynne, wynne. Nether yet, as it is ſounded of the commune people in any of theſe two words folowyng: wyde, wynge. Alſo y, beynge a woorde counteruayleth the ſignification of (the) in Engliſh: and of <hi rend="small">Le,</hi> in French, or of the articles <hi rend="small">Ha, Ho,</hi> in Hebrue &amp; Greke, as thus: y dyn, whoſe propre ſignification in Englyſhe is not communely vſed, excepte a man ſhoulde ſay, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but <hi rend="small">Le homme,</hi> ſhall well declare it to any that ſhal be ſkilled in the French.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="pronunciation">
               <head>Of the letter <hi>Z.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Z</seg>, In Walſhe is vnknowne in ſo much that it was neuer placed in anye walſhe worde hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto: Neither neaded I once to ſpeake of it but bycauſe I woulde put the reader vtterly oute of doubte in this behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="guide_to_abbreviations">
               <head>Of the Abbreuiations.</head>
               <p>&amp;, ꝯ, Be neuer vſed in the Walſh, neyther occupy they but few breuiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſillables, but write euerie ſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ſaue only in ſome propre names of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they do in theſe: Eden<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for Edenyued: Eign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eigion: Gro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for Grono: Gr. or <abbr>Gruf</abbr>, for Gruffith: Ieu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n for
<pb facs="tcp:2069:27"/> Io<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan>, for Iorwerth: Ken<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for kenwryck: Lln<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Llewelin: <abbr>Mad</abbr> for Madock: <abbr>Tud</abbr> for Tuder. &amp;c</p>
               <p>Whiche kynde of breuiations be not vnworthy the markinge of all ſuch englyſhe men, as ſhall be eyther pregnotaries, clarkes, or counſaylours in Wales.</p>
               <p>For I do remembre that once a clarke (being but a yonge begynner) at an aſſiſe in oure countrye, redde a mans name beinge (ſhorte written) Eden ap Iorum wher he ſhould haue read it Edenyuet ap Yorwerth And ſo the crier called ſtyll, Eden ap Iorum come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the court, or loſe .x.li. that ſhalt thou loſe, for thou was ſene here euen nowe.</p>
               <p>And true it was, for the perſon that was ſo oft and ſo loude called, ſtode ſtyll all thys whyle euen at the cryers back, and anſwered not at al (being ſo ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſnamed) vntil he had welmoſt loſte amerciment. At whych feact (the geſte at the laſte perceyued) was there no ſmale laughter of all the whole courte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rules">
               <head>A briefe rehearſall of all the rules be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with certaine other additions therto pertaynynge.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the pronunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letters in Walſh to the pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Greke &amp; Hebrue letters.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>, Is mooſte vnlike of pronunciation to the Hebrues Aleph.</p>
               <p>B, mooſte entierly reſembleth the nature of Beth.</p>
               <p>C, and K, be not vnlike in ſounde vnto Caph &amp; Koph. Ch, chi, cheth, and caph with caphe, be of one ſounde. D, ſoundeth as Daleth Dagheſſata.</p>
               <p>Dd, conteyneth the power but of one letter, and that of Dhelta, or of Dhaleth, not Daggeſſet.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>E, is much ſpoken after the ſound of the vowels Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gol, or Epſilon.</p>
               <p>F, and Beth, withoute the poynte Dagges, or the Greke Veta, be as one in ſounde.</p>
               <p>ff (or) ph, agre in pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation with the Greke Phy, or the Hebraick phe, not poynted wyth Dages.</p>
               <p>G, is ſounded as Gimel.</p>
               <p>H, and thaſperation he, be equal in power.</p>
               <p>I, in euery poynt agreeth wyth the Greke iota.</p>
               <p>L, Lamedh, and Lambdha, diſagre not in ſound.</p>
               <p>Ll, countreuayleth Lambda co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming before iota.</p>
               <p>M, N. mem, nun, and my, ny, differ not in ſound.</p>
               <p>O, and Omega ſhall ſounde as one</p>
               <p>P, doeth as well imitate Phe and Phy in ſounde as in other conditions.</p>
               <p>R, hath a peculier concinuitie with Rho.</p>
               <p>S, Samech, and Sigma maye go togyther well i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe for their tune.</p>
               <p>T, ſoundeth as Teth, or Taf in the Greke.</p>
               <p>Th, hath the verye ſounde of Theta or Taf hauinge no Dages.</p>
               <p>V, beynge conſonante ſoundeth as Beth wythoute Dages or as Veta doeth.</p>
               <p>V, beynge vowell is read as Kubuts and not muche vnlyke vnto Ypſilon.</p>
               <p>Y, hath the verye ſounde of Ypſilon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="comparisons">
               <head>What concinnitee the Letters in Walſhe haue wyth the Greke letters.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſemethe not only expedient for the learner hereof, to compare the pronunciation of the letters, to the Hebrues phraſe of ſoundyng, but it is alſo requiſite &amp; no leſſe neceſſarie (for hym that hath a ſyghte in the Greke tongue) the ſame alſo to ſort after the diuiſion of the Greke letters.</p>
               <p>Wherfore we call four of the conſonantes thynne, bicauſe they include no maner of aſpiration in them: And the ſame foure ſhal we call thyck, whan they are aſpirated, of whom alſo thre be called meane, or mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle lettters, and that whan they be nether thyck, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet thynne.</p>
               <p>The thynne letters be theſe: k p t l.</p>
               <p>The thycke letters are theſe: ch ph ll.</p>
               <p>The middle letters, g v dd.</p>
               <p>And as theſe letters in the Greke inflexions do paſſe one into an other, ſo haue they in Walſhe, ſuch like al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration.</p>
               <p>The mutable or chaungeable vowels be theſe: a, w.</p>
               <p>The mutable conſonantes be theſe: b p c, or k d ll m t. And all the reſte as well of the bowels as of the conſonantes be vnmutable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sounds">
               <head>Of the ſounde of ch, g, i.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ch in wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe is but one letter</note>Theſe thre letters, ch, g, i, haue neuer the like ſounde in the walſhe tong, as they haue in theſe englyſh wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, chere, gentle, iack.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="contractions">
               <head>Of contraction vſed in Walſhe.</head>
               <p>I-o ſhal be contracted into o, longe, or into aw: as digio, digo, or digaw: llidio or llidaw. And ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traction is more peculier vnto the Southren
<pb facs="tcp:2069:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> Walſhmen, than to vs of Northwales.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="accent">
               <head>Of accente.</head>
               <p>The obſeruation of accente is it that ſhall do muche towarde the attaynynge of the natiue pronunciation of any language, in ſo muche that ſometime the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of accent ſhal altere alſo the ſignification of the word, as in theſe wordes in Greke: <hi rend="small">Neos, Tomos, Pharos.</hi> and theſe in walſhe: gwydd, gwyll, gwyr: and in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe: theſe, differ, prouide, denye. &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="examples">
                  <head>Certayne Engliſhe wordes wherof ye may gather the Walſh pronunciation of the letters.</head>
                  <p>Archangell, Beynge, Called, Michael, Diſcomfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted* Dde, Euer<note n="*" place="margin">F for V</note> Fillaynous, Fend, Gget, Him,<note place="margin">Dd for th</note> Itch I-eldynge, Keſt, Laye, Mellttt, Murmurynge, Not, Ouer, Preuayled, Rauenynge, Horrible, Satanas, Tormented, Thorowe, Valeant, Buſines, Worthy, Yll.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="examples">
                  <head>Theſe be wordes wherein the letters be moſt vnlikely ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to the walſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of them.</head>
                  <p>All, Combe, Dombe, Ceaſſe, Cyue, Checke, Adder, Ele, Fyſhe, Gender, Engyn, Humoure, Honour, In, Iaundice, Fall,<note n="*" place="margin">The bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de.</note> Oſyll, Reaſon, Seaſon, Thomas, That, Vncle, Ydle, Syngyng.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="signification">
               <head>The ſignification of a, in Walſhe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>,</hi> in walſhe ſet before an interrogatiue reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betokeneth (whether) in engliſh as thus: a d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daw ef, a y ynte ni ddaw? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is (if I might ſo wel phraſe it in engliſh) whither wil he come
<pb facs="tcp:2069:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> or whether wyll he not come? A y hwn yw ef? is this he? A y hon ywr vwlyddyn vecſes? is this the biſext or leape yeare? But ye muſte marke that ſometime a, in Walſhe is the forther piece of ac, whyche agreeth in ſignification wyth (ac) in latine, and wyth (and) in Englyſhe: And thys coniunction ac, in Walſhe, ſet in conſtruction before a worde that beginneth wyth a conſonaunt ſhall put away c, and ſhall be reade after the onli power of a, as thus. Deo a Mair: vn a dau, and not Deo ac Mair, vn ac dau.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="signification">
               <head>The ſignification of Y.</head>
               <p>Y, betokeneth in Engliſhe (the) as thus: y gwr, the man: y wraic, the woman. And when y, cometh before a verbe, it betokeneth (ther) and if the verbe or word that foloweth after the y, begyn wyth a vowel, than ſhall there be added d, dd, or r, vnto the y, for to ſtop the ouermuch gapinge that the metynge togyther of the to many vowels ſhould els haue cauſed, as thus: yd, oedd, ydd, oedd (or) yr, oedd, there was. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme y, include th in it ſelfe ſuch a relation as ſchin in the Hebrue doeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rule">
               <head>A generall rule for the readynge of Walſh.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough there be diuerſe precepts heretofore written of the Walſhe pronuntiation of the letters, I woulde thinke it not ouermuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſonant nor yet to wyde from the purpoſe, to admoniſh you in this behalfe, that is: that you ought
<pb facs="tcp:2069:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> not to reade the Walſhe accordynge as ye do the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe or Frenche, but euen after the readynge of the latine. For in readynge Englyſhe or Frenche, ye do not reade ſome wordes all ſo fully as they be wrote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>And in manye other ye ſeme to ſounde the ſillables more fully than the expreſſed letters do geue. Which maner of readynge is ſo vtterly eſchued in walſh, as ye perceyue it to be exactly obſerued of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitely reade the latine tong: Neyther do I meane here to call them perfite and latinelyke readers as manye as do reade: angnus, mangnus, for agnus, magnus, ingnis, for ignis: ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus, for ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctus, ſawl for ſal: ſowl, for ſol: and for mihi, meichei: and egow for ego: tuw for tu: and quith ligith, in ſtede of quid legit. &amp;c. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye muſte learne to forget ſuche maner of pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation agaynſte ye prepare youre ſelues to reade the walſh. More ouer ye ought to know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe words dringo, gwingo, kynga, myngen, anglod, angred: and the moſt part of ſuch lyke walſh wordes hauyng ng, in them, and beynge of moe ſillables tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oue, ſhall be reade as theſe Englyſhe wordes be (but ye muſte ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite them to be reade nowe as of two ſillables euery worde) Kynges, rynges, bryngeth, ſyngeth: For euen as ye do not reade them: kyn-ges, ryn-ges, bryn-geth ſyn-geth: but rather in thys wyſe: kyng-es, ryng-es, bryng eth: euen ſo do weſounde: dring-o, &amp; not drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go: gwing o myng-en, and not myn-ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Albeit yet as ng, maye be ſeuered and parted in this engliſh word ſin-geth (but the ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altered) ſo haue we ſome wordes in walſhe (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ſpoken) in whom the ſillables may be ſeuered in ng, as in theſe: an-gerth, llan-gwm, trin gyrch. &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ore ouer maiſter Colingborn, thys ſhalbe further to certify you, that mine intent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was not to inſtructe or to teach any man abſolutely the walſhe tonge, but rather to let the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der haue a ſight of it (as it were thorow a latteſſe) and to proue whether it were poſſible for a man to come to the naturall ſpeach of a language, wyth the onelye introduction of preceptes. For I meane nothing leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to go about to enduce any Engliſh man to learne Walſhe (but for hope to attayne ſo muche engliſhe of ſuch in permutation therof) but contrarily I would fayne wyth all induſtry endeuer my ſelfe to helpe and further all Walſhemen to come to the knoweledge of Englyſhe,<note place="margin">Engliſhe</note> as a language moſte expediente, and moſt worthieſt to be learned, ſtudied, and enhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, of al them that be ſubiectes, and vnder the obeyſaunce of the imperiall diademe, and triumphante Sceptre of Englande, euen for the attaynement of knowledge in Gods word, and other liberall ſciences whyche tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the benifite of the learned men of our dayes be communely hadde and ſette forth in the ſaid Engliſhe tongue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Walſhe</note>Agayne as for the Walſh tong euen as it is not now to be compared wyth the Englyſhe language, ſo is it not ſo rude, ſo groſſe, nor ſo barbarous, as ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers beynge therein all ignorante and blynd do adiugde it to be: nor yet (to ſpeake indifferentlye wythout all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections) is it not all ſo copious, ſo fyne, ſo pure, nor ſo fully repleniſhed with eligancie, graces, &amp; eloquence, as they them ſelues ſuppoſe it.</p>
               <p>Howebeit whan the whole Iſle was commune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2069:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> called Brytayne, the dwellers Brutes or Bryto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glande Schotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; Wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les were called Britaine were the Walſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours called Brytons</note> and accordyngelye their language Brytiſhe, I wyll not refell nor greatelye denye, neyther can I iuſtelye gaynſaye but theyr tonge than was as copious of fit wordes, and all maner of propre vocables, and as well adournated wyth worſhypfull ſciences, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable knoweledge, as anye other barbarous ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſtyll continued (thoughe their Septre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, and theyr Kyngedome decayed, and they alſo were driuen into the moſte vnfertyll region, bareneſt contrey, and moſte deſert prouince of all the Iſle) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll the conqueſt of Wales. For than (as they ſaye) the nobles and the greateſte men of the countrey beynge captiues, &amp; brought priſoners into the tower of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don there to remayne durynge their liues, deſiered of a commune requeſte, that they myght haue wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſuch bokes of their tonge as they moſte delited in, and ſo their pticion was hearde, and for the lightnes ſone graunted, and ſo brought with them al the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalleſt and chiefeſt bokes, as wel of their owne, as of other their frendes, of whom they coulde obtayne any to ſerue for their purpoſe: whoſe mind was none other but to paſſe the time and their predeſtinate, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual captiuitie in the amenous varietie of ouerrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and reuolueynge manye volumes, and ſondrye bokes of diuerſe ſciences and ſtraunge matters.</p>
               <p>And that is the commune anſwere of the Walſhe<note place="margin">Barde.</note> Bardes (for ſo call they their Poets or rime makers) Whan a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal obiect or caſt in their teath the folyſh
<pb facs="tcp:2069:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> vncertaintie and the phantaſticall vanities of theyr prophecies (whyche they cal Brutes) or the doubtful race and kinde of liuing of their vncanoniſed ſayntes: whom that notwythſtandynge they doeth inuocate and worſhyp wyth the mooſte hyghe hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noure and lowlieſt reuerence.<note place="margin">Lhyfreu Kymry ai llo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frudd, Ir twr gwyn ay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thant ar gudd, Yſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celer oedd i Scola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Vwrw .r twr o ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freu ir ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gutto .r. Glyn.</note> Addynge and allegynge in excuſe thereof, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reliques and reſidue of the bokes and monumentes, as well of their Sayntes lyues, as of their Brutyſhe prophecies and other ſciences (which periſhed not in the tower (for there they ſaye certayne were burned) at the inſurrection of their contrye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell Owen Glyn-door: were in like maner deſtroyed, &amp; vtterly deuaſtat, or at the leaſt wyſe that there eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped not one, that was not vncurablye maymed, and irrecuparablye torne and mangled.</p>
               <p>But hereto it mighte rather appertayne to ſpeake to renewe, and call to remembraunce the diligent and curious obſeruaunce of olde antiquiti, as concerning exact pronuntiation and ryght ſoundynge of wordes ſillables, and letters, whych euen the noble nation of the Grekes (who excelled all other nations in euerie kynde of good learnynge) dyd not once neglecte to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, practice, and duly execute for the wontynge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſynge, and perfeictinge of the tonge of youthe, to the ende it ſhould not ſo eaſely ſtomble, ſtagger, lyſp, or relent beſyde the iuſt and true ſoundynge of all ſuch letters, ſillables, and words, as were hard to be ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the ſtraunge concourſe and vnwont metynge togyther of the ouer manye conſonantes in the ſame: Of whych ſorte the Grekes haue many words, as it appeareth in thys verſe.</p>
               <q>Graun chtho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian aes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hros phthonos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ouxiphos e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hthrou.</q>
               <pb facs="tcp:2069:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And ſuche verſes be called of them <hi rend="small">Chalepoi.</hi> that is: harde to pronunce accordynglye. And the Latines haue deuiſed them for the ſame purpoſe thys other verſe. <q>Arx ſtridens roſtris, ſphin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſter torrida ſeps ſtrix.</q> And the diligence of the aunciente Engliſhe men hath found out (to auoyde the volutable and ſlypper lapſe of the tonge in ſoundynge togyther a meyny of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des conteynynge in them diuerſe conſonantes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke pronunciation) thys compacte of wordes &amp; ſuch other like. Three beanes in a bladder, rattle bladder rattle.<note place="margin">The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xons cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led firſte the Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhemen</note> Alſo the Brytons (I meane them whom the vnlearned and the commune ſorte of people call ſtyll in the old Saxons terme Walſhmen) of like regard haue ioyned togither certain words for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: whyche who ſo euer ſhall redilye, roundely, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitelye ſound: the ſame ſhall alſo pronounce more eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye all other wordes: And ye ſhall take thys nowe for one harde ſentence in Walſh, but to be ſpoken round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye: Paam y bydd garw blayn blew barf gafyr? am y bod yn pori bric helyn garw gardd bardd baron. &amp;c. Here is an other of that ſorte but ſhorter: Barkutan yn pigo pupur. An other as harde. Kiffill ar ben gallt y piſtill. Theſe examples maye ſeme to ſome men not onely vulgare and chyldiſhe, but alſo vayne, vnfrute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and no leſſe folyſhe: and ſo be they in dede (and what is not ſo, beinge abuſed or miſtaken?) if they be not applyed to the directed ſcope and purpoſed inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But nowe who ſhall be ſo vnlucky as to leape ouer a blocke and ſtumble at a ſtrawe? And who is he that ſhal diſtincly pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Douch Bildtſchuitzer, but the ſame ſhall ſone pronounce Verdampt? What ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is he that can ſounde Wyncheſter Englyſhelike, but
<pb facs="tcp:2069:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> coſequently ſpeake hault or ſuche other lyght word? And ſo who is he that can ſpeake thaboue wryghten walſh ſentences and can myſſe of the pronuciation of other wordes of moare commune conſtruction? And bycauſe (as I proteſted befor) I do not entend to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you nor anye man els,<note place="margin">Brytyſhe miſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe.</note> than is ouer deſierous to the ſtudye of Brytyſhe (I meane the language that by continuall miſnomer the recorder of the aunciente hoſtilitie is called Walſhe) I wyll not once ſpeake a a worde in praiſe of it (thoughe and if I were learned I myght ſay ſomewhat to it) but willingly wil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit to ſet forthe what ſelect wordes, what conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and fine termes, and what ſentencious and net adages, whych the olde, ſage, &amp; learned fathers haue not only inuented, but alſo of the Grekes and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines moſte proſperouſlye haue taken, tranſlated, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and vntill thys daye ſtil retayned: I wyl omit to declare any white of the manifolde retorical phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I wyll winke at the tropes, metaphores, &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, and ſuch maner of ſpeaches whych the Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſhe tonge hath as commune,<note place="margin">The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge</note> yea rather as peculier or ſiſterlyke wyth the holy language.</p>
               <p>And as for to conferre the pronuntiation of them both togyther I wyll not: for, what ſhuld I make a compariſon betwexte whyte, and euen like whyte? or liken an egge, to an egge? And if I ſhoulde but once enter to treat of the vnſpekeable felicitie, and the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous graces of the Brytiſhe meters (who his inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable obſeruatiue compoſition,<note place="margin">Loke els in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte leafe</note> no man but bi the onely gifte of nature hath euer attayned) I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make an ende.</p>
               <p>But nowe after thys, oh, howe it greaueth me to
<pb facs="tcp:2069:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſcloſe the vnfayned trueth, and to confeſſe the vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimuled veritie, that there remayneth now but walſh pamphlets for the goodly Brytiſh bokes, ſometyme ſo well furniſhed wyth all kynde of literature: and ſo fewe Brytyſhe fragmentes of the booke of Chriſtes owne religion remaine vnwormeaten,<note place="margin">For if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel be hyd, it is hid amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are loſt. ii. Co. iiii</note> and defended from iniurye of tyme, and the booke of Howel da ap Cadell ſo longe preſerued ſalfe and ſounde? Yea, it is rather to be lamented and greatly to be ſorowed to ſe howe fewe Walſhemen haue the knoweledge of the Englyſhe tonge, whyche as by the next way mought nowe reſtaurate for the outworne baren Britiſhe, the reliques of the noble Britons to their euer affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate knowledge, and accuſtomed learnynge of good letters, pietie, and godlines.</p>
               <p>But nowe maiſter Colingborne, leaſte peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where I thynke my ſelfe but familiarly to talke here with you, and other my familiares (as my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge is none other in dede) ſome thankeles taunter entermeddle and ſay vnto me, alludyng to that mocke of Diogenes. <q xml:lang="lat">O viri Myndi portas occludite, ne quando vrbs veſtra egrediatur.</q> meanynge thys thereby. O my good frende haue done wyth your Walſhe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles haue done: for els your ioly <hi>prooemion.</hi> and your goodly <hi>parergon</hi> ſhalbe len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than al your boke beſyde: Here therfore at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt I make an ende.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addition">
            <pb facs="tcp:2069:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An addicion.</head>
            <p>The maner of one kynde of meter in the Britiſhe tonge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">DISTICHI BRITANNICI POLYMETRI RATIO THEORETICA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Genus metri.</p>
            <p>Ciccanet croes cyſne Widoc.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>chart of cynghanedd meter</figDesc>
               <head>The name of the metre ¶Cyccanet traws</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="roman">HARMONIA</hi>
                  <lb/> Cu adardy coed ir dec<lb/> 
                  <hi rend="roman">CONCENTUS</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="roman">TAVTOGRAMMATON</hi>
                  <lb/> 
                  <hi rend="roman">HOMOEOPTOTON</hi>
               </p>
               <p>CYCCANET<lb/> Cwvert hardꝭ mewn cyvair tec<lb/> The verſifienge</p>
            </figure>
            <p>An other kynde of meter.</p>
            <q xml:lang="wel">
               <l>Pop gwlat aeth [orat vn a thri] De braint / </l>
               <l>I brintio mewn trevi.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">['sef o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rat De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o]</note>Nio anos mewn Daoni</l>
               <l>Bot yr vn gwaith in Iaith ni.</l>
               <l>Aehi caradd ac cant.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
